all right where should you look for
information about HTML and CSS and web
development you probably have already if
you started to ask yourself this
question you know that the internet and
a random Google search is going to
inundate you with a ton of crap and I
mean crap there is a bunch of really
horrible documentation out there and I'm
going to tell you rtfm my friends
rtfm read the fancy manual and what do I
mean by a fancy manual um the best place
to learn web development is from the web
specification and this is a lot of
people try to like uh you know make up
different different ways of doing this
and they end up failing and I'm going to
show you what I mean by that so
unfortunately W3 schools it's funny
because there used to be this okay so W3
schools is not a bad thing right um it
does organize a bunch of the code but
you need to understand that this is let
me just tell you about this so W3
pools um W3 fools was once they have CS
now uh W3 school is this this is
actually this every time I see W3 uh
which is they completely owned the SEO
to have it pop up but it's important
that you understand that this resource
has historically sucked bad um it has
been a really horrible place to go it
had a lot of people from the officially
from the community who who took it who
made W3 fools because they were so put
off by how hard it was uh they had to
actually change this and saying they
have largely resolved these issues
largely resolved does not mean
completely resolved so again if you are
being sent here and by the way I do I
regularly go here to look up a little
thing that I can't figure out but that's
really not the official source and it
does kind of annoy me that the searches
don't even find the official source so
the uh W3 uh working group um we won't
get into the history of the working
group The W3 working group um working
groups are the heart of the w3c w3c
historically has been the place to go uh
for they actually literally created the
specification um unfortunately there was
also they didn't keep up I mean it's
it's hard for you to know about this um
there's w3c and then there's another
thing called the W3 working group which
was created primarily from people from
Google um uh
W3 uh why why isn't it you know what I
think I think it's because the working
group finally resolved their drama and
said no go to w3c for
everything um I think they finally went
ahead a lot of people have been
recommending M
Milla uh okay so here it is the HTML the
HTML working
group um I'm trying to think
w3c
uh uh working group HTML working group
I'm trying to find it it's actually hard
okay let's see chartered until
blah I mean I'm kind of Interest where
is it how come it's still so hard to
find
uh yeah HTML has had problems in the
past
[Music]
um so okay let's let's actually just go
look at this history of uh web
specifications okay including HTML so
the w3c was the original one and then
they stopped updating stuff and
everybody was like why can't they do
anything they become completely unusable
and so the um the the other group came
up and they said we're going to do it
instead and this is not accurate at all
and but they came up with HTML
5 um so HTML 5
and this I'm actually kind of glad we're
having trouble here because it's so hard
to get the actual documentation there it
is what WG that's the one I was looking
for I was looking for it's what WG okay
so this
so I gotta I got to tell you about this
because you're going to get confused
you're like what the hell is the what
WG um okay so the what
WG in fact let's let's go let's go there
let's go to the what WG uh and let's see
what they have to say about what they
are um all right so okay the maintained
and evolved HTML since 2004 so the short
answer to this drama in the history is
very simple the original organization
that that created the absolutely
horrible xhtml standard um which is pre
HTML 5 um was the w3c and there were so
many problems with with it and I'm going
to get negative comments there's no way
around it and I mean it was bad there
were they tried to push a bunch of
really bad ideas and the whole world
pretty much all the developers were like
no this is absolutely horrible it's
almost like they don't actually use the
specification of the technology that
they're creating which is largely true
the specification body became
disconnected from the developers who
were actually using it and by developers
I mean the the largest representation of
developers which included the Googles
and the most zillas and the and the
microsofts and all of those people uh
they were the ones doing it all and and
so that became the the you know these
these people that were making the web
browsers uh and that were having to deal
with this HTML it was kind of a
disconnect because w3c I I promise you
this is going to relevant to where you
should go learn right because you need
to know the history you need to know the
history of why this is the most
definitive source for Learning and how
it came to be that way um so so the w3c
which was making all the they were
specifying everything but they they
weren't involved with making any of the
web browsers at all and so the web
browser manufacturers were over here the
working group The what WG working group
they're like well we want the blink tag
and we want this and this and this and
this right and you know the Milla
Network that they got um all of it right
and and so they're like screw you w see
we're going to do our own thing and they
released the HTML 5
specification um and that became the
living standard since 2004 and they
basically took over from the w3c without
even asking they said look we make every
major browser on the planet and we are
going to tell you what our browsers can
do and then you're going to decide
whether you want to get in line or not
and fast forward
um
to uh to like let's actually look at
there's a here we go uh the hyper Tex we
is a community people interested in
evolving the web through TS and tests we
finded by individuals from Apple Milla
uh opens Opera software in 2004 after
the w3c workshop uh Apple Milla and
Opera were becoming increasingly
concerned about the direction of xhtml
lack of interest in HTML because it
sucked uh so in response these
organizations set about with a mission
to make it better uh in 2000 so this is
important in 2017 Apple Google Microsoft
and Milla helped develop an IPR policy
on government structure of
wwg um and as far as like God it sounds
like they took it
back okay so so last time I read this
last time I read this there was a thing
that said by the way we're singing
Kumbaya with w3c again and w3c is in
charge again but it seems like there's
no I don't see I
don't I think they might have changed
their mind again
I think they might have said nope nope
w3c doesn't know what they're doing it
takes them forever to get anything done
we're just going to keep it there used
to be there used to be a fact here that
said that that they do it you know what
let's ask chat GPT what chat GPT has to
say um uh what is the
relationship uh between
w3c uh and what uh WG believe it or not
this is going to answer the question
about where you should learn HTML
because you can't answer the question
seriously people you can't answer the
question about where you should learn
HTML until you know who's in charge of
defining the
standard right w3c the worldwide Web
Consortium and what WG web hypertex
application technology working group are
two entities that develop standards for
the web w33 is original Tim burners
leeenter of the web what WG started as a
rebellion among browser developers
against the w3c due to his frustration
over slow progress I already said that
the Rebellion resulted in the creation
of HTML 5 which is wildly accepted as
really awesome uh HTML 5 is an amazing
standard uh for many years W wgm did
work separately uh each with its own
version but in 2019 there it is they
announced an agreement to work together
to create a single version of HTML known
as the quote Living standard maintained
by what WG but officially endorsed by
w3c this development marked an important
unification how the web standards
developed in other words w3c said yeah
we're good you do it yeah yeah you're
good rubber
stamp rubber stamp rubber stamp because
they had no power they lost all the
power every single browser manufacturer
had decided to join what WG and so w3c
is like
huh so they joined
it that's exactly what happened um
anyway so this is where the standard is
so read read it for yourselves my
friends read the HTML living
standard um this by the way includes CSS
uh even though I don't think CSS is is
written here let's go see if we can find
it um okay but anyway um CSS is actually
a part of the standard um I wonder if
it's listed under the different standard
compatibility console Dom the document
object model is something you'll need to
know eventually
um HTML infra MIM snipping what I don't
know about these other ones URL what is
the URL what is URL standards web
sockets which is super cool if you're
going to do any kind of web games you
need to know
it uh don't use the Mozilla dos
everybody says to use misila do and they
are dramatically out of date and wrong
uh I know this firsthand I've used the
Milla do many times I've actually
submitted Corrections which remain
uncommitted um I'm telling you people
read the manual and and most people will
say but the manual is too hard to read
it's actually not look right here read
the HTML living standards let me let me
let me test you on this how many people
think that the Bold tag and the italic
tag B and I are actually no longer part
of the standard I guarantee you at least
one person listening to this will be
like B and I are you're not supposed to
use them because they're documented
incorrectly uh in different places and
so again go to the standard and I'm
going to say it again in all cases go to
the standard get used to reading the
standard docs get used to reading rfc's
get used to reading go finding out what
the standard is and going there every
time you read somebody's interpretation
no matter how well intended no matter
how well funded whether it's W3 fools to
I'm sorry W3 schools or it's Mozilla or
it's Microsoft you're always getting
somebody else's interpretation of the
specification when instead you could
have learned it correctly by reading the
specification no matter how much extra
work it takes to do that that goes for
everything it goes for The Bash man page
if you're going to learn how to do bash
shell scripting best to learn it from
the man page which was written by The
Bash people not somebody's third-party
book that you had to pay money for
that's not even correct anymore okay so
I mean this is a little bit of a rent
but it's it's annoying because people
are constantly recommending their
favorite replacement for the actual
standard
okay and and I'm telling you right now
go to you've never heard what WG because
you didn't seek out the standard right
the actual standards body that's
responsible for defining the standards
for the entire worldwide web that is
contributed to by every major browser
manufacturer should be considered the
company the authority to refer to and if
you don't know about it I'm sorry but
this is the standard and now you know
now you know if I'm if I'm sounding a
little bit you know passion or like
triggered or something it's because I'm
so annoyed that professionals don't know
about the professional specification for
HTML even though they're being paid to
know how to code in HTML and do web
development about 50% of the web
developers out there have never even
heard what WG is they could never even
tell you where to find the specification
and yet these people are writing
applications every day for the for banks
and for Netscape I mean Netflix and for
all these other organizations so yeah
you're going to see me rant about this
read the and manual read the manual know
where the manual is know who wrote the
manual and find who has the manual there
I'm done all right so this is the
manual uh and it doesn't work in half
the browsers and it doesn't matter to
you yeah well in this case that's not
the case this case 10x programmer this
actually is the standard and the
standard was created by the people who
made
the browser so pay attention make sure
you learn it don't get left in the dust
that's all for this video